Guide to the William Henry Morse Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Henry Morse papers
1833-1959
MS 25
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
The papers include personal and family correspondence, subject files, and photographs relating to the life and career of William Henry Morse. The collection also contains genealogical material relating to Morse family members, particularly Jedidiah Morse, the father of American geography.
Morse, William Henry, 1846-1940
Existence and Location of Copies
Selected images have been digitally reproduced and are available through the Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database.
Related Material
Morse Family Papers, MS 358. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, 1850-1959. II. Fraternity Activities, 1833-1927. III. Legal Registers, n.d. IV. Subject Files, 1854-1925. V. Photographs, 1863-1921.
Biographical / Historical
William Henry Morse, born in 1846, was the son of Richard Cary Morse (Yale 1812), the grandson of Jedidiah Morse (Yale 1783), and a nephew of Samuel F. B. Morse (Yale 1810). A graduate of the Class of 1867, he served as class secretary from 1867 to 1940. After graduating from the New York University School of Law in 1870, Morse practiced law independently in New York City until 1874. He then studied stenography and became one of the first court stenographers. With the exception of short periods of employment elsewhere, Morse worked as a stenographer, reporter, and instructor in shorthand until 1897. He then held the position of night librarian of the Supreme Court Law Library in Washington until his retirement in 1930. In 1879, Morse married Louise Parish Townsend. The last surviving member of the Class of 1867, Morse died in 1940.
Scope and Contents
The papers include personal and family correspondence, subject files, and photographs relating to the life and career of William Henry Morse. The collection also contains genealogical material relating to Morse family members, particularly Jedidiah Morse, the father of American geography.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Morse, Jedidiah, 1761-1826; Morse, William Henry, 1846-1940; Morse family; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1867; Yale University -- Societies and clubs; Yale University -- Students; Zeta Psi Fraternity. Eta Chapter (Yale University)
- Correspondence, 1850-1959, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of two parts: Family Correspondence and General Correspondence, each part arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. Family Correspondence includes correspondence of family members with William Henry Morse and with each other. General Correspondence consists of materials from non-family members.
  - Family Correspondence
    - Correspondence of William Henry Morse
      - Austen, Alice (Ally) (niece), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Colgate, Austen (nephew), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Colgate, Gilbert (nephew), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Colgate, Russell (nephew), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Colgate, ... (sister?), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Daris, William H. (uncle), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Delafield, Lily Morse (niece), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - League, collective letters, 1915-1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Morse, Anna C. (sister), 1920-1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Morse, Harriet H., 1881 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Morse, Libby (sister), 1891 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Morse, Livingston B. (cousin), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Morse, Louise (wife), 1857-1893, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Morse, Marguerite (niece), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Morse, Marie Louise (daughter), 1910-1925 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Morse, Mary C., 1920 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Morse, Molly (sister), 1884-1893 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Morse, ...(mother), 1857, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Morse, O. C. (Olly) (brother), 1870, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Morse, Richard C. (brother), 1900-1926 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Morse, Richard C., Jr. (Dixie) (nephew), 1919, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Morse, R. C. (father), 1850-1865 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Morse, Rebecca (Becky) (sister), 1887 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Morse, Sidney E. (brother), 1900-1959 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Morse, ... (brother), 1881 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Parmele, Louise Morse (sister), 1857, 1889-1891 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Pamele, M. L. (Meddie) (niece), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - (Penny, H. L.) (aunt), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Pope, Asa (nephew), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Robertson, Jessie L. (cousin), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Robinson, Gerald L. (cousin), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Roome, Oscar, Jr. (distant cousin) [to folks, newspaper clipping], 1920 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Townsend, Samuel, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence of Morse family members with others
      - Morse, Louise from L. S. Augusta, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Morse, Louise from P. L. S. Cornelia, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Morse, Nolly to mother, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Morse, O. C. to Morse, R. C., 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Morse, R. C. from Apthorp, E. D., undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Morse, Richard C. to Colgate, Austen, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - General Correspondence
    - Apthorp, E. D., 1857 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Bonney, S. W., 1854 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Burrell, David James [newspaper clippings], 1909-1910, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Clark, Charles Hopkins [newspaper clipping], 1923 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Claxton, J. H., 1891 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Collin, A. P., 1909 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Curtiss, Ethel, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Dillenbeck, M. H., 1897-1920 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Douglas, R. A., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Dunning, Charles, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Duyckinck, W. C., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Flanders, Roger Y., 1906 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Hart, S. R., 1902 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Hodge, Eddie, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Kitchel, Mary, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Know, (George W.) Express Co., 1901 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Miller, George, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Mills, George C. [telegram], undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Neely, M. M., 1928 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Rahrl, Magdalena, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Reid, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Shepard, Frederick J., 1910 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Wild, Isaac J. [newspaper clipping], 1920 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Williams, Edward H., Jr., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Williamson, Roland, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Wright, Henry P., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Fraternity Activities, 1833-1927, Series II
  Fraternity Activities contain correspondence, lists, and notes pertaining pertaining to the Phelps Association, fraternity affairs, Skull and Bones, Scroll and Keys, and honorary societies.
  - The Phelps Association, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence concerning fraternity affairs, 1916-1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fraternity societies [membership list of Skull and Bones, Scroll and Keys], 1833-1875, 1902-1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Honorary societies [lists and notes], 1906-1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Legal Registers, n.d., Series III
  Legal Registers contains reports. Included are chronological registers of American and English reports by George E. Harris, various British colony reports, periodical reports, and a list of abbreviations of titles of legal periodicals.
  - Chronological register of American and English reports by George E. Harris, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - English reports arranged [section 1, 2], undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Reports [English, Victorian, New Zealand, Irish, Scotch, Canada Law sections 3-12], undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Periodical reports, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Biographical [abbreviations of titles of legal periodicals], undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Subject Files, 1854-1925, Series IV
  Subject Files contains notes, registers, reports, lists, speeches, newsclippings, and printed materials. Included are family documents; obituaries and material concerning Morse family genealogy; Yale history and reminiscences; and materials relating to William Henry Morse's professional concerns.
  - Family genealogy, ancestry notes, will and testament of William Morse, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Family genealogy, register of Jedidiah Morse, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Morse, S. F. B. [information concerning his radio experiments], undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Family expense list, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Andover Class of 1863 [reunion speech], undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Curriculum and class standing of William Henry Morse at Yale [copy], 1910 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "College Reminiscences" of William Henry Morse, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Certificate of reliability, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Library of Congress [sick leave cards], 1925 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Notes concerning political life in Washington, D. C. [with newspaper clippings], 1920-1921 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sympathy cards on the occasion of the death of wife, Louise Morse, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Notes concerning the interment of wife, Louise Morse, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Wilkinson, John F. N. [assistant law librarian of Congress, obituary, newspaper clipping], 1912 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Wedding announcement and picture of a home, 1880 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Notebook with shorthand notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Notebook with shorthand notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning ancestors and Yale, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Photographs, 1863-1921, Series V
  Photographs are arranged by subject matter and alphabetically within a subject. Oversize photographs are at the end of the series.
  - People
    - Austin, Alice, 1883 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Delafield, R., undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Hewins, Miss, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Hodge, Charlotte Morse, and Louisa Noyes Hodge, 1890 December (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Hodge, G. A., undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Morse, Maria, and Maria and Gertrude Morse [glass negatives, consult Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database, image numbers 5477, 5480-5483], 1900 Nov, 1901, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Morse, Maria [nitrate negatives discarded, consult Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database, image numbers 5484, 5485], 1901
    - Morse, Marie Louise, 1883-1885, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Morse, Marie Louise Townsend, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Morse, William Henry, 1863, 1916, 1918, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Morse family [glass negatives, consult Manuscripts and Archives Digital Image Database, image numbers 5478, 5479], 1901 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Morse family members, undated (Box 4, Folder 11 - 15)
    - Pope, Asa P., 1893 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Places
    - Augusta, GA, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Brandon, VT, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Chicago, IL [World's Columbian Exposition], 1893 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Nantacket, MA, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Narrangansett, RI, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - North Carolina, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Vassar College, NY, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Various places, 1894, 1895, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Various places, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Postcards
    - General, 1910, 1921, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Yale and New Haven, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Oversize
    - Houses, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Individuals, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Needlework, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Scenes [land, water], undated (Box 5, Folder 32)